Hello and welcome back to Off the Fence
with myself, Constantin, Francis Foster,
of course, Winston Marshall of the
Winston Marshall Show, and last but not
least, Tom Slater from Spiked. Welcome
back, lads. Good to have you. Our four
stories for today are war with Argentina
potentially. Javier Malay says Argentina
will prevail over declining Britain.
We've got the reformed donation scandal,
the Lindsey Clansancy case, and of
course Andy Bernham is back. and uh
better than ever presumably we will find
out. So let's get into our first story
that is of course Javier Malay saber
rattling saying that he will prevail or
Argentina rather will prevail over poor
declining Britain. Um could we be facing
war over the Falklands with Argentina?
Well a few quick things introducing the
story. Uh there may be other dimensions
going on here. So, President Trump very
bitter against the UK's lack of
involvement in trying to reopen
Australia from US apparently has
signaled that he's prepared to
reconsider uh America's neutrality on
this. There's some oil considerations
which we'll talk about and of course we
will discuss Britain's military capacity
to actually deal with this problem. So,
first and foremost when how do you feel
about Argentina saber rattling over the
forklins?
You're going to start with me, are you?
Brilliant. Well, I'm extremely triggered
about this issue. I'm sick to death of
this what is essentially Latin American
Palestinianism.
The Falklands are British. We saw it
[laughter] first, right? The first
written European sighting is John Davis
in 1592. We were the first to set foot
there in 1600. No, sorry, I've got that
date wrong. in uh 1690 with John Strong.
Right. This is British now. It's been
British longer than the Argentines have
been Argentinian. It is it exist. It was
British before Argentina existed. Not
only that, there have been several polls
where 99.9%
of the people of the Falklands want to
be British. They are ethnically British.
The indigenous people of the Falklands
are British. Not only that, we have had
considerable blood spilled because of
this continued claim by the
Argentinians, of course, talking about
the Falklands war. I was at the
Argentina game in the World Cup and I
had these Argentines shouting my face
about Las Menus and Argentinis nonsense.
They're British and it's actually
offensive. I have friends who are
veterans from that war that they're
still banging on about. This is uh uh
just makes me makes me very angry. And I
I just want to add that there's a few
other things that have come out in this
story. Benjamin Netanyahu's son, which I
know you got in a spat with KK this
week, has come out on the side of the
Argentinians trying to provoke us
because of the British government's
response to Israel throughout the the
the war with Hamas.
But it's it's completely contradictory
from him his point of view because it is
Palestinianism. Firstly, we have the
longest claim to the to the island.
Secondly, the people there want to be
British. That they are British. And
thirdly, like Hermas, Argentina keeps
starting wars. They can't win. And a lot
of people die along the way. So, it's
not entirely a joke. So, anyway, I I'm
pretty annoyed about this whole thing.
And I'd add to it. I'm not confident
that our prime minister Burnham is going
to have the balls of Thatcher to stand
up to this antagonism.
>> Well, in addition to lacking the balls,
I mean, one of the things that I did is
I was quite curious because I don't know
if you saw there was a story in I think
in the Telegraph earlier this week about
the fact that the British army is now
cancelling live fire drills. And we're
not talking about for reserves. This
this is a a prominent uh front fighting
division. Uh they're cancelling live
fire drills to save money. So the
preparedness of the British armed forces
to do anything about this irrespective
of the political will is an interesting
question. So I actually I looked this up
on Venice AI and and it's a mixed
picture. Um the garrison on the Falkland
Islands is much much stronger than it
was uh 40 years ago at the time of the
Falklands war. At the time there was
only 80 servicemen on the islands. Today
we have somewhere between 1,300 and 1700
including helicopters, fighter jets etc.
Um the problem is the navy. So the 1982
task force had 127 ships. There is now
only 63 ships in the entire British
Navy.
>> So we are at half of the task force now.
And so, uh, Britain could realistically,
>> can I just add to that?
>> Yeah, go for it.
>> Constantin just on the 63 ships in the
Navy. If you actually look at aircraft
carriers, frig uh, and destroyers where
it's far fewer. I mean, it's only two
aircraft carriers. I think there's only
six destroyers and and maybe eight fri I
don't show the exact number off the top
of my head.
>> Well, it's worse than that. So in terms
of what we could deploy, in terms of
what we could deploy now, it would be a
carrier, two destroyers and five
frigots. And the first sea lord, General
Sir Gwyn Jenkins, I suspect he might be
Welsh, has stated that the Royal Navy is
not ready for war. So uh that's one
side. On the other hand, I also got
Venice to tell me the Argentinian
numbers, and this is where it gets
really comical. They basically have
nothing. They have no [laughter] navy
whatsoever.
And so it'd be like I was thinking what
what the it would be like the battle
between Stephen Hawking and Hamza not
Hamza Ysef Abu Hamza the one with the
hook. [laughter] So we would we would be
in the role of Abu Hamza in this
situation slightly slightly advantageous
[laughter] but but both crippled. Um so
so irrespective of the political will I
just think Tom militarily
>> when Javier Malay slags us off and says
he they're going to triumph over
declining Britain it's sort of hard
there's there's part of that where you
can't argue with it.
>> Yeah. No absolutely and on the one hand
it is kind of not saber rattling like
plastic saber rattling like no one
really expects something to properly
kick off here. Neither side could
actually wage any kind of conflict. I
have been thinking though in tandem with
the story that we're going to talk about
next forklands and and reform hitting a
lot of controversy. It's been a very bad
day for gammons in Britain, you know,
and I share in that sadness, you know,
two very crucial important things there.
But yes, I mean to see what um Javier
Mille kind of play on our kind of
relative weakness, even bringing up the
question of migration, how we're kind of
internally weakened and so on and so
forth. On the one hand, he obviously has
a point. um the British armed forces,
not just the Navy, but in general, has
long been sort of four BS and a packet
of quavers. Uh there's very little that
we could possibly project even that we
like to pretend that international
summits that were a terribly important
player. But um it's also a reminder
though, isn't it? That even though we
shouldn't expect any kind of
confilgration anytime soon, that we're
increasingly in an era in which hard
power resources
um are of increasing importance and also
that there's a lot of players on the
world stage who are dropping the
pretexts of international law and
agreements and whatever and just going
for the raw assertion of what they seem
to be their interests, their territorial
claims, what have you. And we're just so
fundamentally illquipped to deal with
that kind of environment. So while I
don't think it's about to kick off over
the Falklands anytime soon, it's a
reminder of the kind of era that we live
in and how our politicians are so almost
uniquely incapable of reckoning with
that in the broader sense.
>> Well, you say you say you're not
convinced it's all about to kick off,
but I I would put it to you with what
happened in Venezuela with the fact that
Trump is clearly behind the scenes very
pissed off at the UK not providing
support for the efforts to reopen the
straight uh and is signaling to have
him. I mean, we've got a clip of Ham
Malay. Look at this. He looks exactly
like Vladimir Putin announcing the
special military operation in 2022. Look
at this.
Now I will correct myself and I mean, he
he's if you read the subtitles, it looks
like Vladimir Putin. If you look at his
hair and and also Spanish just is not as
intimidating as Russian, let's be
honest. Francis, you're you're token
Latin American famously.
>> Finally, I get finally I get a chance to
speak right about about one of the
nations from my continent. Oh, and by
the way, Winston, it's pronounced
Malvinus. Malvenas.
>> Don't you start.
>> Anyway, listen. Right. This is the
problem. I had a video that went viral
at the time of the uh at the time of the
World Cup about the Argentine football
team in which I basically said that they
were representative of their nation, a
terrible country. I think the actual
quote was a nation of and I stand by
that 100%.
Because nobody in the whole of South
America likes Argentina. [clears throat]
They've always always always thought of
themselves as above their station.
They've always thought of themselves as
this great power within South America.
And you can see this by the way that
they actually behave. Like
Argentina is a country that has for the
vast majority of its existence has been
broke. It has been absolutely broke. It
has suffered record levels of inflation.
Now, Malay has actually done a good job
in managing to turn around the ship, but
the reality is his approval ratings are
very, very low. They're not where they
used to be. He's in real danger of not
getting reelected. So, for him, this is
a very cunning strategy in order to play
to the jingoistic elements of that
country, of which there are numerous, in
order to get him reelected. I don't
think there's anything really in this. I
think this is, as Tom said, glorified
plastic saber rattling in order to make
himself look strong, powerful, and
relevant. And also taking a bash at the
English, who are always the great nation
that Argentines have always hated. We
are the pantoime villain, and what
better way for him to make himself look
strong and powerful than taking a little
dig at the English. I think uh it's the
case firstly you're absolutely right
that all of South America hates
Argentina. I went to the Mexico England
Mexico game and all the Mexican fans are
like we don't mind that you beat us just
beat those bastards from Argentina. Like
everyone in South America hates hates
Argentina. Uh but the the difference I
think when it comes to this is how weak
the British are at the moment. As we've
already stated, John Healey, who
resigned from Starmmer's cabinet as
defense secretary because they weren't
going to meet the 3% of GDP defense
spending, has now as Chancellor Dick
Checker kick the defense spending
commitments down the can for a year. Not
only that, you've got the uh Trump is it
seems to be more on the Argentine side
of this because he's so pissed at us
over Iran, not letting them use RAF
Fairford, not letting them use Diego
Garcia in uh the Chos Islands. So, we're
not in a good position there. He he
might try and antagonize us more. I
think Argentina in as good a position as
they could. They've been since the
Falklands war to actually do something
here.
I guess I guess we'll see. I also note
that for them this is the every time
they're in trouble, whoever's in
government, they bring up Las Malinas,
as they call it. This is this is the one
thing that unites the whole country.
It's it's the it's it's a real central
point of
Argentine nationalism. I mean it it's
it's the same sort of thing with the
Palestinianism where you have this
grievance uh at the at the very core of
of their identity and I think that's the
same with Falkland Island. It's a
grievance that unites the country and is
is the core of their identity.
>> My my worry is that you I I worry that
we we may be underestimating here
certainly Francis and Tom the the moment
we're in in terms of the possibility of
this actually becoming much more real. I
mean, first of all, there's some oil
interests involved here. And I don't
know if you guys caught pres Vice
President Vance's press conference
yesterday. He kept talking about the
fact, well, yes, the stray isn't quite
as open as we'd like to be, but that's
why Venezuela was so important.
Actually, 130 miles off the coast of the
Falkland Islands to the north, uh, is uh
a an oil field called Sea Lion, which
has way more oil in it than either of
the two major fields in the North Sea.
They're due to start uh production of
these fields in the next two years. And
one of the things Malay specifically
said is they will sanction the British
and Israeli oil companies that are set
to explore this. My point being is oil
control of oil in in the in the Western
Hemisphere is clearly something that the
United States is very very heavily
focused on at the moment. Um and uh
combined with the fact that the current
administration is willing to tear up
conventional norms about who our allies
are and who our enemies are. Um I I I am
concerned that this actually may be
something real. And look, I've been
saying this for many many years. Uh
probably so many times Francis has got
bored of hearing it. But there is a very
simple rule to geopolitics is if you
signal weakness, you invite violence.
And we've seen it over and over uh all
over the world. And my worry is, as I
said from the beginning, when when
people like Malay talk about Britain as
a declining nation, they're kind of
right. And if you are a declining
nation, people will start to have a go.
>> They'll start to test you. Absolutely. I
mean, it's one of those things which
we've been telegraphing to the world. I
mean, I forget the exact date that Kan
put on it when he was still in power,
saying that we need to be ready for war
by X date. As if to say, [laughter]
"Hello, Russia. Hello, you've got this
window in which to exploit. And the fact
that as we've already been talking about
this, we're in this bizarre situation
where we've got this new chancellor who
obviously resigned as defense secretary
precisely because Karma and the Treasury
couldn't stump up the money to reach the
3% of GDP by 2030 target is now
incapable of saying in public, John
Healey, he resigned over this issue and
yet now as chancellor, he cannot tell
anyone categorically that we will meet
precisely that 3% of GDP target by 2030.
And that's even without getting into
whether or not these kind of arbitrary
targets are actually even going to
translate in the kind of capabilities
deterrent which is actually going to be
effective. You see across other NATO
countries where a lot of kind of
creative accounting takes place and you
know the pensions of military personnel
or whatever suddenly starts to take up a
outsized proportion of what
[clears throat] it is that supposed to
be that three or ultimately 3.5% of GDP.
So, we're still playing these quite
silly games, kind of rhetorical games.
Meanwhile, whether or not it's the
Faullands, or whether or not it's
something else, um we're just so clearly
not capable of even just even just
creating the impression that we might do
something, let alone actually doing
something, which is a big problem.
>> And I think very interesting, sorry, go
for it. win.
>> Uh the there was a story last year about
how we'd been we spent billions on Ajax
tanks, but tank warfare is just not
relevant anymore. And you'll remember
also at the beginning of the Iran war,
HMS Dragon was sent out a week after our
bases in in Cyprus were hit. And then it
it had to come around and it turned
around in the end because it wasn't it
wasn't ready. Our money is being
misspent. We don't. It needs to be We
need to have a proper navy as
Constantine said earlier, but we should
be investing in drones. We should be
investing in actual tech that's useful.
Tanks aren't useful and tanks aren't
going to be particularly helpful if
we're at war with the Falklands.
And look, the problem is as well is as a
country, and we'll come to this in the
fourth story where I will talk about
Andy Burnham and Parliament reconvening
is that we're broke. We don't have the
money to let alone spend not just to
spend on defense but to spend on our own
country because what we need to do is we
really really need to tackle the def the
deficit that we have. We spend a huge
amount on just interest alone on the
debts that we owe. And until we actually
make those very difficult decisions,
which successive generations of
politicians have refused to do, we're
simply not going to be able to fund our
defense in any way that is adequate.
Yeah. Well, we spend more on welfare
than we raise in income tax. Um, so that
will tell you quite a lot about the
position we're in. Uh, Win, go for a
last word before we move on.
>> Well, just on your point there, Francis,
if we had a proper look at defense
spending, actually, you could increase
the size of our armed forces and
military. It would give employment and
it would it would create it would wean
people off the welfare welfare state. By
the way, this is what happened in the
Second World War with FDR. I just had
James Holland on the show uh discussing
this. But actually if you you can
actually use a proper defense strategy
to pull people away from welfare create
employment and the massive added bonus
as well as having a bloody defense that
would protect our small islands is that
you create national unity you actually
give something for everyone to get
behind. So I think it's it's a frame of
mind not even just a financial thing.
It's it's it's how we look at our
defense and how we think about our
defense.
>> Well Francis says we have no money left.
You know who has some money? It's reform
cuz they've got a lot of donations. Uh
hey, good transition. Uh but seriously,
there's been a story, actually front
page story now in all the newspapers, I
think, and on the BBC, which is that two
senior reform officials have had to res
step down pending an investigation into
their conduct after allegations of
unlawful activity in relation to two
donations. Uh Tom, do you want to tell
us more about this story before we get
into the debate?
>> Absolutely. I mean, this is the biggest
story in town, not least because it
coincides, of course, with Reform UK
Conference, which is kicking off in
Birmingham as we speak. So, there was
this investigation which was put
together by an organization called
Verbatim, which is basically a offshoot
of something called the Center for
Climate Reporting, so you can kind of
understand where they're coming from
politically, and Channel 4. And
essentially the journalist in question
or the campaigner in question depending
on your perspective posed as the sort of
British son of an American businessman
who was looking to contribute to reform
in any way that they could financially.
and he's got all of this footage
primarily meeting with James our the
head of policy at reform who's one of
those officials who has just stood down
pending this investigation as well as
Dan Juke who for more than a decade has
essentially been Nigel Farage's kind of
closest aid right-hand man maybe kind of
would be chief of staff if he ever got
into Downing Street and essentially it
boils down to because of the electoral
law prohibiting foreign companies from
making donations to British political
parties this would be an arrangement in
which and what seems to have happened is
that a a poll would be commissioned. It
would be paid for by again the the
British son of this American businessman
and that that was a this is being
presented as a potential breach of
electoral law, a kind of way to get
around what the letter of the law says
in order to enable a donation in kind if
not exactly in in form as it were. And
it's now naturally turning into a big
enormous story. Um I think there is a
couple of things I'd lay out about this
before we get into it. One of which is
that um I think we do have an increasing
problem with scandal mongering as a kind
of political weapon in British politics
and British media. And what I mean by
that is not to say that in all instances
there's no bad smell to a particular
story that there is no story that there
is no potential wrongdoing. It's just
that something is taken, sort of leapt
upon, turned into a kind of totalizing,
unprecedented, never-before-seen kind of
story, and then used as a stick with
which to beat in particular populist
upstart often right-wing parties. Um,
meanwhile, you know, it doesn't take a
particularly long memory to remember
that after the 2015 election, you had
the Conservatives fined more than 70,000
for failing to declare or not properly
declaring around like £300,000 worth of
donations. There's a whole kind of labor
together scandal which I could bore
everyone to tears by explaining but
basically again boiling down to a kind
of very pro-Sarma think tank the people
who led it ending up being key parts of
the Star government again failing to
declare large amounts of donations and
then crucially also commissioning a
organization to produce a report to
discredit the journalists at Sunday
Times potentially who had produced those
allegations and published them in the
newspaper. So, I'm not trying to sound
like a kind of cynic. Everyone's at it,
whatever. But at the same time, one one
must always take these stories, first of
all, subject them to scrutiny. This is
um not yet a kind of cut and dry legal
case by any stretch of the imagination,
but also kind of putting it into
perspective so that the it doesn't allow
itself to be too weaponized. The other
part of the story though of course is
that I think reform have often said and
rightly so that particularly as they
were looking like they were spoiled to
you know potentially win the next
election dropped off in polls a little
bit since then but still have been the
kind of preeminent party of government
for much of the past year that the media
that various wings of the establishment
were going to throw absolutely
everything at them. And in that
environment you've got to be as cautious
and as squeaky clean as you possibly can
be. You certainly can't invite this kind
of thing. And also just sort of you know
whilst the the full details are yet to
come out you do wonder whether kind of
the the basics of due diligence would
have avoided this kind of story from
ever taking place. So as ever I think
it's as ever with stories like this
there's a lot that we don't know there's
a lot that we'll still find out. There
may well be a there there, but whether
or not it is the totalizing this proves
they're rotten to the core, that is
something that I think we need to deal
with a to take with a huge amount of
skepticism because I think we've seen
that story play out over and over again
and it's often not in proportion to the
scales of the allegations that have been
leveled at them. I think one of the
things actually that this story has
shown and it's disappointing for a lot
of people who support reform and support
the issues that reform raises is the
lack of professionalism when it comes to
the organization itself. As I was
watching Channel 4's expose, I was
thinking to myself, well, who was
vetting? Why weren't these people
properly vetted? And if they were, why
weren't they exposed as to who the And
I'm talking about the undercover
journalists. Why were they allowed to go
in and just have direct access to Nigel
Farage? I really couldn't imagine this
happening with the Conservatives. I
couldn't imagine it happening with
Labor. To me, it just shows just how
inexperienced and in some ways naive
reform actually are. That they're
prepared to have these types of
conversations which are highly
sensitive, possibly legally
incriminating, and they're just prepared
to have these conversations openly with
people that they barely know or have met
a few times. It's really, really, really
worrying for reform. And you have to say
on the back of the Times expose which I
think looking back on it was a bit of a
damp squib possibly these things are
cumulative and I don't think it's going
to hurt reforms base who will always
vote for reform but what I think it will
hurt are the floating voters who have
been disappointed by 14 years of to put
it bluntly inept and incompetent Tory
rule and a couple of years of Labor
proceeding to essentially throw their
opportunity away as well. So, it's
deeply worrying and potentially
potentially a body blow to reform's
chances of getting elected in the next
election. Like I said, not because it
affects the base. I don't think it will,
but those floating voters, it's another
one in the minus column.
>> Yeah, it'll be interesting to see
whether it is a body blow. So I think of
Trump particularly in his period out of
office between the his two terms and
they [clears throat] threw everything at
him. They were, you remember, various
sort of investigations and they were
going to Mara Lago to sort of
investigate things and they were all all
sorts. They threw the book at him and
what it did to the American public is
actually made them more inclined towards
him because they felt like the blue
stack was against him and and and there
is an element of that going on here. Uh,
look, so if I were to break this down, I
agree with you guys watching the video.
It's sloppy from James O and and Dan
Jukes and
they said some things which are not
great. Uh, I'd also note that it's a
heavily edited video, so we don't see
everything. I also note that the case of
the s, so it's a British son of an
American father.
If this had not been sloppy, there's
nothing I don't think there's anything
legally wrong. If the American father
had said, "Right, son, I'm going to give
you some money. It's up to you what you
do with it. I know you like reform. You
can give it to them if you want. It's
not my business." And that would have
been I I don't think that's illegal. I I
and it would have been fine. And so why
they didn't just make it as simple as
that if they were going to do that
route,
it it seems uh a little bit strange to
me.
So that's one side of it. I also note
that the organization
uh as you as you say Tom, it's a center
for climate reporting. These are this is
a foreign these are foreign funded. So
it's a it is a version of foreign
interference into uh British politics
about and they're claiming it's about
foreign interference because it's it's
the money side. So there's a kind of
hypocrisy here. I'd say that the it's
Channel 4 have have legitim sort of
verified uh this work. Uh but it is very
much activist. So these are activists
working against reform. I see it as part
of a
uh the what Dominic Cummings described
sort of everyone throwing the book at
the reform party or the sort of uni
party trying to destroy them. I think
that uh you mentioned in passing uh Tom
that there there's examples of this kind
of stuff happening with other parties.
Yeah, there is there's been there's been
foreign money coming to the Labor Party
for example there was uh Gary Lubnner
story when when there was 6.5 million
from Johannesburg to London and they
kind of you know he became a UK resident
and or there was a Cayman Island hedge
fund who gave 4 million quid to Labor
after their election
>> in 2024. So there's foreign money going
to the other parties. Uh and I I'm I I
imagine this kind of stuff's happened
with the tries as well. Uh but they they
kind of left themselves exposed here. Uh
uh reform. Um I uh would also note and
and this is important time the times and
the telegraph who published that polling
without checking into the source of it.
They look bad in this.
>> JL partners the polling company look
terrible in this. like absolutely I mean
I think they're finished or if they're
not finished there heads have got to
presumably roll to if they want to
preserve themselves as a as an entity.
Uh so there's a lot of people who look
bad in this um whole thing. Uh, and I'd
also say the problem with for reform is
James O who full disclosure I'm friendly
I'm friends with and uh I I actually
think he's a very honorable man and um
this is this what we see of this story
isn't in keeping with the man I know. Um
uh I think that he's actually key for
reform. He is he brings them a
intellectual rigor and robustness that
makes reform seem serious and and so to
lose him would be significant. There's a
report that Lee Anderson has says that
has said that who's the MP for reform
has said that James or and Dan Jukes are
permanently gone. I'm not sure if that's
confirmed. It looks like there's further
investigation into the story. Um uh but
uh it is um it's not pretty. Uh my
frustration personally is that Britain
has got some very very serious problems.
our current government and we have a new
prime minister who had his first week
sitting and and first PMQs this week is
under a fraction of the scrutiny of this
insurgent party who only have a handful
of MPs that we we
you know we're in serious problems and
we're going to come to Burnham later so
we we'll cover it then but the people
who actually have power are not getting
the scrutiny they deserve and the uni
party the blob all of these are focused
on reform trying to destroy it because
reform are calling out some of the
problems our country has and for me
things particularly immigration I don't
hear this that it's certainly not being
dealt seriously with uh from from the
Labour party. So my frustration is if we
want to actually sort our problems out,
we we're in a double fight trying to
make the problems clear and having the
the the blob attacking those types of
parties
in any any way they put sort of uh can
>> just to tack on to that because I think
it's so clear now that this is
essentially one of the sort of weapons
in the toolkit to try and do with
scandal what the establishment has
failed to electorally or via kind of
conventional means which again is not to
suggest that this you know that the
press should go easy on reform by any
stretch of the imagination that they
shouldn't be subjected to scrutiny but
in the in the middle of a kind of media
mastrom it's very easy for a narrative
to set hold when the plain facts might
not support the level of scandal which
is being discussed like as you were
saying there Winston like the again the
kind of finding of kind of neat ways in
order to make sure that a poll can be
paid for it's the sort of thing which
might look a bit grubby might smell a
certain way but at the same time in the
grand scheme of things is not the kind
of image of corruption which is being
presented as um that said it's not to
say that it still can't do damage that's
the unfortunate kind of power of the
media in these sorts of situations and
also the fact that this could have led
to immediately just that that those
resignations whether or not they're
permanent is a question that we have to
wait for the thing I would add is that
whilst of course James or slightly more
recent recruit to the party and has
become very central as you say Winston
in terms of building out the policy
offer the kind philosophy of the party,
what have you. Dan Dukes has been ba
basically by Farage's side for more than
10 years and is someone who everyone was
particularly surprised to have seen
stepping down in the manner that he had
and Farage then going on LBC this
morning and referring to both Dukes and
Ore as contractors of the party. So
whilst we await to hear what is going to
happen with this internal investigation
and where the dust is going to settle,
um, it's clearly already landed a blow
rightly or wrongly onto the party as it
goes into this conference. So yeah, it's
the political consequences have been
pretty significant. This is part of the
problem is that in the midst of the the
media ma suddenly you get a a narrative
that is set which to a certain extent
the stepping downs have played into
whether or not that was the intention.
>> Well see this is where I I've agreed
with pretty much everything everyone
said to this point but this is where I
actually have a different view on it
because to me those two stepping down is
a clear indicator. Look I I'm not a
legal expert. I can't say what's legal
and what's not, but the fact that Nigel
Farage, who said to our faces only a
month ago, I'm really loyal to the
people who are loyal to me when we
interviewed him. The fact that these two
men have resigned, to me, that's an
admission of guilt. Personally, just as
an outsider, that to me is what it looks
like. The fact that he's been prepared
to lose Dan Jukes, who's effectively his
right-hand man, as people have said, and
James or who is as central to reform as
we've discussed already. That to me is
them basically saying we've screwed up
here and we have to put distance between
ourselves and the story by getting rid
of these two people who are really big
assets
>> in in their perspective to their party.
So from that perspective I think it is
an admission of guilt. But I also think
the context that all of you actually
have presented so far is really
important because you know what this
reminds me of. It's like in Russia and
forgive me Tom you mentioned you're not
this cynical everyone's at it. I am this
cynical partly because of my background
and partly just because of what I think
the reality is. Uh I actually when last
time I was staying at Winds I pinched
his copy of Michael Crick's biography of
Nigel Farage which is by no means a
flattering book to Farage
>> but Crick repeatedly details how the
Tories cheated over and over in
bi-election after bi-election when
contesting seats with reform. Mhm.
>> Now, what does it was? Yeah, definitely.
>> UKIP as UKIP. That's right. As as it
was. My point being is everybody does
cheat. And this is why I actually never
get excited about any of these stories.
We had a discussion last night about
about whether we actually wanted to
cover this at all. And I think the thing
that actually tipped us over the edge is
the resignations. Yeah. Because if you
take that out of this, what you're
looking at is, let's be honest, a fairly
trivial story about some
behindthe-scenes shenanigans about
sourcing a bit of money. And by the way,
this is another thing that is actually
very disappointing if you are someone
who's reform aligned or reform curious,
you might say. We're talking about tiny
amounts of money.
>> Yeah. Americans will be shocked as to
how little we're talking about. Like 30
grand.
>> I know. Look, 20 grand [laughter] is a
lot of money for for ordinary people and
for all of us, but for a political party
that is seeking to become the government
of the country,
>> all of this over 20 grand to do a poll.
It just it seems a level of risk that
forget about the morality of it. It's
not remotely commensurate with the with
the potential gains of of this. Go
ahead, win. I have more to
>> just one point on that. Yeah. So it's a
tiny amount of money in in respect to
the money paying for polling, but the
hit job was expensive in terms of paying
for a hit job. So they paid 30 grand for
the polling.
>> Okay. Sorry, I'll let you make the point
then. Well, well, what I was going to
say is so there is this broader context
which is basically everyone's up to it,
but I just I think the thing that that
you see here is reform are kind of
amateur-ish when it comes to this and
that it's not a surprise because they're
an amateur new party, but it's
disappointing nonetheless. And then on
top of that, we have to talk about the
angle of this. This is it's not a
coincidence that the Reform Party
conference is starting today. This is a
deliberate hit job by a far-left
anti-Net zero pro-Net zero activist
organization. Channel 4 had nothing to
do with this. These activists did all of
this work and then brought it to Channel
4 who then went, "Oh, yeah, it looks
decent. Let's let's get it out there."
Uh, and what you're seeing, as Tom
rightly said, I think is uh the the
media class doing what electorally the
political opponents of reform couldn't
do.
That said, you know, if this is properly
investigated by the police, given the
evidence that we've seen, it would not
be surprised me if there are potential
prosecutions out of this because let's
be honest, the footage is not a good
look at all.
>> Yeah. Which also wouldn't be
unprecedented. It's worth saying, which
is not to create excuses for anyone and
just to try and rebuff any accusations
of double standards or hypocrisy here.
Certainly if you look at the way that we
at Spikes have covered various of the
kind of stories involving the
Conservatives, even the the Labour
Party, um we're essentially apply the
same level of skepticism to many of this
these stories. A lot of this scandal
mongering like even when they were going
after like Angela Rainer over a stamp
duty or going after Kier Star over Lord
Ali buying his wife dresses for some
bizarre reason. Um, again, what was
embarrassing there was the hypocrisy.
They were running on being whiter than
whites, on complete polar opposite to a
supposedly grubby Boris Johnson. They
got caught out. But I think whenever you
have, you know, beyond clear-cut obvious
corruption, money being used to
influence policy in a nefarious fashion,
politicians becoming bought mouthpieces,
um, influence being bought and pedled in
a really kind of clearly undemocratic
and unsemly way. Of course, everyone's
against that. But when you get down to
these kind of more fine grade
distinctions around electoral law,
ethics, procedures, what have you, what
tends to happen is it tends to empower
the law, the state, or some kind of
quango at the expense of democracy. It's
like what we need is more rules. What we
need is more ethics committees. What we
need is more laws that would baricular
political parties if they overstep the
mark in this way, that way, or what have
you. So again, as ever, outside of
clear-cut examples of corruption, which
everyone is is against, there's when you
get into these kind of finer
distinctions, loopholes, bit of wheeler
dealering, bit of, you know, creative
accounting in order to get around what
might be the um the spirit of a lot of
the regulations.
This can very easily be be weaponized. I
think we need to be on our guard against
it regardless of of where it's coming
from. And if you reform, you need to be
on your guard against not falling victim
to these sorts of efforts to entrap you
when they come along. Definitely.
>> And also, look, and I think you've made
a great point, Tom, this is politics.
This is the game of politics. Once you
get to a certain level, once people
start recognizing you as being a
legitimate threat to them getting into
power, whether it's Labor or
Conservative, these shenanigans are
going to start. And really now this is a
moment for reform where they have a
choice of whether they go down the
similar route that they did which is
sort of the you know the wheeler dealer
you know let's
let's play at what we're doing here you
know we can be a little bit woo a little
bit we a little bit geyserish and we can
you know make our way and all the rest
of it or you're going to actually now
professionalize
and think to yourself we can't do this
anymore. If you want to get into power,
if you want to lead this country, then
quite frankly, the whole organization
needs to up their game and there needs
to be far more stringent. They need to
start professionalizing and they need to
start looking at who the people are that
they're interacting with and really
really doing some stringent checks cuz
this can't happen again. This is a
massive wakeup call for everyone
involved. It's a potential body blow,
like I said before, particularly with
the floating voters, but I don't think
this is the end for reform. This is a
chance for them to go right. We can get
better, but it means we're going to have
to make some very tough decisions, and
it means we're going to have to take out
and eliminate some of the kind of wide
boy antics that you can see in this
video. Well, the the the thing is that
while that may all be true, I think as I
mentioned that given the small amount of
money involved, uh, you know, I remember
having a conversation with a just a
randomly bumping into a very senior
media executive at a at a function of
some kind and them saying to me, well,
the problem for reform is they just
can't raise the money that they need.
And so, you've got these competing
things. You say, "Well, they've got to
professionalize." What? We know this
from our own experience running
trigonometry. What What does
professionalize means? It means you have
to hire people who are better than the
people that you have. Uh that cost
money. Where do you get the money? From
donations. How do you get donations? And
then you're back to to where we started
this entire conversation. To say nothing
of the fact by the way that I, you know,
I agree with Winston, we know James
personally. James our is a very decent
and principled and moral man. So for him
to have found himself embroiled in this
smacks to me either of desperation or of
slip of standards or or whatever. I
don't know. But my point is I don't
think it's as easy as you know get a
grip and sort it out. Like there are
structural issues going on here which is
for a party to be successful you have to
raise a lot of money. And as we've
already talked about you're not
competing in a level playing field.
Everyone else around you is cheating
while not being subjected to the same
scrutiny. And this is what I was going
to say from my Russian angle. It it
reminds me a little bit of what happens
in Russia where effectively everyone is
guilty but your guilt is identified and
investigated not when when it sort of
the police miraculously discover that
you've been doing something wrong but
rather the when the powers that be
decide that now is the time for you to
be exposed. And so what you have is the
the the completely uh unbalanced
application of these rules and norms
because I guarantee you
>> I guarantee you that if independent
journalists, which these people were
not, these were activists were spending
tens of thousands if not hundreds of
thousands of pounds trying to entrap
Labor officials and trying to entrap
Tory officials and trying to entrap the
officials of other political parties and
similar schemes. they would all come out
with egg on their face. And the only
reason you're not seeing that is that
those efforts are not being made
equally, but rather they're being
targeted or reform because they're seen
as the enemy.
>> And also just to add to that, the extent
to which the rules aren't being applied
or the rules of engagement aren't being
applied equally. Also, the rules around
and the law around donations, the Labour
party been trying to change them
precisely in response to reform doing
quite well in relation to donations.
It's one of the many things that Andy
Bernham has had to kick into the long
grass because he's just got too much to
deal with at the moment. And there was a
story earlier this week. They kind of
realized that some of the proposed caps
on donations would have potentially
affected the Labor party's coffers in
terms of the union. So naturally that oh
we got to rethink this now. But um again
that not only are the the standards not
necessarily being applied equally, the
government is has been trying in real
time to change the law so as to scupper
the insurgent threat from reform. So all
of that is very very real and it's like
how you deal with that, how you kind of
scale and also how you do what reform
been trying to do which is which is
genuinely unprecedented in Brit British
politics which is to go from five MPs at
one election to potentially being a
majority party at the next one. We've
never seen that before and and the of
course that's going to come with it a
lot of thrills and spills and arguably a
bit of corner cutting. That's not to
excuse any wrongdoing and any alleged
criminality if that is what comes out of
it, of course. But that's the context in
which all of this has has happened. Um,
and it's at least worth bearing in mind
when we look at the full picture of
this.
>> All right. Well, moving on to uh I was
going to say let's go to something more
light-hearted, but unfortunately this
being a topical news show, it's it's all
downhill. Uh, next story is uh, of
course, the story of Lindseay Clansancy,
the trial of Lindseay Clansancy, and
Winston is going to bring us the
details.
So Lindsay Clancy killed her three
children in January 2023 and the murder
trial has been underway
these last weeks. And we have had now
another day where the jury are
undecided.
Neither the prosecution or the defense
are disputing that she killed her
children. Neither the prosecution or
defense are disputing that she is
mentally unwell. What they are disputing
is whether this how cap how culpable she
is
in knowing and perpetrating the
killings. So it's really a question
between whether this is first-degree
murder, secondary degree murder, or
manslaughter. I I don't think it's a
question about a quiddle, although
technically that could be uh what the
jury decides. So it we're it continues
to go on. So that's the the very core of
it. But at the next sort of level, you
then have a bunch of people,
bunch of women, not just in America, but
here in Britain, as far away as Peru,
South Korea, Portugal, who are coming to
her defense
>> in the the millions has been raised um
to to vend to defend her. They all
wearing pink and they're outside the
courthouse protesting
>> and they are claiming that she is the
victim that the real culpab culpability
lies at the feet of the industrial uh
sorry uh the the
medical institutions that failed her. So
it is the case that she had been seeing
various professionals uh for psychiatric
help. Uh this isn't uh just made it
isn't made up post hawk that she had
these illnesses. There is a there is a a
a track record of her having postpartum
depression. And it seems that I don't
even think postpartum depression is in
dispute right now. So the but what's
disputing is is how culpable she is. And
then there's another
uh sort of secondary or tertiary
offshoot to this story which is that the
a lot of men or a lot of women are
reporting on social media on Reddit and
and beyond that
their boyfriends or even fiances are
calling off weddings or ending
relationships because when asked about
the Clancy case, they gave answers
dissatisfactory. to the boyfriend. So,
so men are now ending relationships
because they don't like the answers of
the women when it comes to asking their
opinion about what should be done and
what should be the verdict in this
Clancy case. I think that's my summation
of what's happened. Is that is that I
think
>> before we get into the debate uh and I'm
keen to hear everyone's opinions before
I give mine. I think there's a couple of
things that are worth adding factually.
Winston one, it's not just that she
sought different professionals for for
various things. So, by all accounts,
including the the the testimony of her
mother-in-law, who believe me, as as a
married man, I can tell you that is an
as objective a source in these
circumstances [laughter]
as you're as you're going to get.
[clears throat]
According to
>> get the jury, just get her to decide it.
Yeah. prior to well quite prior to the
to the four months in which her mental
health deteriorated. She was uh the a
devoted mother uh a delivery nurse I
believe uh widely respected in her job
and so on. Had no history of violence
towards the children or anyone uh and
was in every way basically a normal
decent person who really looked after
the kids. She was prescribed 12
different medications including
anti-depressants,
antiscychotics, things to treat her
insomnia, I think benzoapony, dasipines
by different practitioners, many of whom
were not in coordination with each
other.
>> Uh and she w she committed these
killings three weeks after being after
coming out of a psych psychiatric
facility. So these these just little
bits of context and the final one which
which will be relevant to my opinion
which I'm happy to give later is her own
ex now ex-husband whose children it was
that she killed uh says that she's not
evil she was just ill. Um I leave it
there for for us to get into the
discussion
>> and just to look at one dimension to it
as well which is the there's a sort of
outpouring of sympathy for Lindsay
Clancy and the kind of the the growing
number of people it seems like who feel
that at the very least she wasn't kind
of culpable in the same way as one might
be if she wasn't suffering from severe
mental ill health as they claim. There's
also of course that kind of
conspiratorial fringe which um basically
rejects the idea that she killed these
children whatsoever. Something that even
her own defense aren't contesting um
completely speirious allegations that
the father Patrick who discovered his
three children killed. And apparently
the 911 call which hasn't been allowed
to be released but was played in court
was so shocking that most of the jurors
were in tears. And even the kind of very
battleh hardened journalists who were in
the room and you know covered a lot of
very very grim cases were pretty shocked
by the kind of prime screams that they
heard. There's there's this kind of
group of people online which you now see
whenever you have a high-profile case
like this. It's a kind of weird mix of
kind of postcoid conspiratorialism and
sort of true crime fandom which has
created this level of uber cynicism in
relation to cases like this. they're
just openly claiming that he did it and
using as proof the fact that he he
remarried relatively quickly after the
horrors in which he he suffered as proof
of that. So so there's that dimension to
it. The the one thing that kind of
struck me is even if we park that
because there's always going to be some
nutters out there and the thing about
nutters in 21st century is that they all
have social media accounts and more of a
platform than they used to have is that
even the kind of outsized level of
sympathy for her or identification with
her is to me quite striking and a little
bit troubling. Like it would be one
thing to say this is an absolute if if
you take as red her defense which is
that she was suffer suffering from this
postpartum psychosis and that as a
consequence of that it wasn't the same
as if she was completely within within
her well mind and just decided to do
this out of evil or what have you. Um,
even if you take that as red, the extent
to which there are a quite large number
of women primarily obviously who see
their struggle in her story, who see
this as part and parcel of a society
which doesn't take mental health
sufficiently seriously. I think is a
little bit off is a little bit strange.
It would be a bit like when we had that
killer in Nottingham a few years ago,
Valdo Calican, who's a paranoid
schizophrenic, murdered three people in
the midst of a very heightened episode.
Again, there were various missed
opportunities to stop him. One of which
was the fact that he was black and the
local authorities were concerned about
putting too many black people in that
form of kind of medicalized confinement.
But nevertheless, it would be it's one
thing to say that's a horrific story.
Um, and of course he was not a well man
when it happened. But to say we are all
Valdo Calakane and to say that isn't
this a damning indictment of the way in
which our mental health services are
failing people? I think we would see as
as an odd response and it's it's
something that you see nowadays growing
when there is a kind of vaguely woke
political script that one could apply to
it. So it's mental health in this case.
You even saw a little bit bit of it in
the wake of Arena Zerutka's horrific
murder on that bus in Charlotte where
you had the local kind of Democratic
mayor come out and suggest that
basically everyone including the killer
was a was a victim in this because of
the failure to take mental health
seriously because he was also clearly
quite a depraved man. So even if we we
recognize the kind of the ambiguity the
complicated nature of this I think that
level of kind of fullthroated
identification with Lindsay Clansancy I
think is a little bit strange. There's a
slight kind of blessed are the murderers
tendency which seems to kick in provided
that there is a kind of political script
it can be folded into i.e. mental health
and how that's supposedly not taken
seriously by society supposedly in this
instance.
>> I I think one of the reasons why this
case has captured the imagination beyond
the obvious is because what it really
talks about and Thomas used the words
mental health when actually mental
health is a catch all term which doesn't
really mean anything. What we're
actually talking about here is mental
illness. And as someone who, believe it
or not, has uh mental illness in their
family. Um, and I've seen my cousin have
suffer from severe schizophrenic
episodes. In fact, I saw her essentially
break down and de develop schizophrenia
pretty much in front of my eyes.
You what it talks to is responsibility.
When somebody is having these types of
severe episodes, which the condition
that Lizzy Lindsey Clansancy is alleged
to suffer from can cause, that sparks a
debate of responsibility. How much
responsibility does the individual have?
How much of it is caused by an illness?
How much of it is society's fault for
not intervening sooner? How much of this
responsibility is belongs to the medical
authorities? How much do these drugs for
instance that the medical authorities,
the doctors that are prescribed actually
work? How much of it do they exacerbate
the condition? And how much of it is
simply that we don't like to talk about
these conditions? And when people are
suffering from these type of severe
mental illnesses, do we just push the
people to one side because we just
simply don't want to deal with it? And I
think that's a lot of what is happening
here and why people are reacting so
strongly to it. Of course, there's the
obvious, the three horrific killings,
etc. Because these are issues that we
are wrestling with as a society in real
time.
>> Winston, you never gave your take on it.
So why don't you give your take on it?
>> Yeah. So, I'll say something that goes
against a lot of the right-wing
commentary here who seem to be very
shocked that this deliberation is taking
so long. I'm actually not shocked that
this deliberation is taking so long. I
think uh seeing as what is not being
disputed is that she's being killed,
what's being disputed is uh the impact
of her conditions on her. Uh for me it's
this is bloody complicated and so uh I
I'm not actually surprised this is
taking so long. I think it's quite
difficult if you're going to make force
me to come off the fence on on on this
one. It's certainly not an uh easy one
to call and I would prefer to do it with
more information and had been in the
court case before coming off the fence
on this one which shows how tricky an
issue it is. But I also think regardless
of what they decide her culpability is,
she should be in prison for a long long
time because as a society we need such
crimes must be punished properly. And so
whe whatever they decide whether that's
some sort of mental institution or or
serious prison for me that's for them to
decide but she should be locked away. I
I she cannot be free. I that that's
where I come off the fence.
Who disagressed
so far, which is actually to me, by the
way, tragic as this story is, I actually
don't think this this should be a new
story at all. The only reason I've had
any opinion on it whatsoever, uh, is the
commentary around it, which both, you
know, Tom and and Winston, you've both
alluded to, which is this, first of all,
this idea that women are quote unquote
defending her. I'm sure there a bunch of
nutters who are defending her. But
broadly speaking, what I see is a lot of
people saying there's not enough
understanding of
what it's like for women postpartum and
some of the hormonal and mental changes.
I give you very small example. It's got
nothing to do with murdering children,
but nonetheless is important. Like my
wife is breastfeeding at the moment. We
have a four-month-old.
She if we I remember literally the other
day we were sitting having breakfast
having a chat about our plans for the
week and then the moment the the little
one latches on she goes baby I literally
can't think right now and I can
literally it's like you know one of
those scenes in a movie where someone in
a big like a server room or a big hanger
presses all the light switches and you
can just see the brain just like the
lights going off. That's what it looks
like. So I think part of the thing that
people are trying to to explain to
people who maybe don't understand this
is the the female brain in these
situations in particular nursing,
postpartum, pregnancy etc. under goes
extreme hormonal changes and in those
situations things occasionally can
clearly go very very badly wrong. Then
there's a lot of evidence. I remember
reading a very long article about uh the
potential for the links between mass
shootings in America and the
prescription of certain antiscychotic
medications. So when you give somebody
12 different medications of all
different kinds in a very short period
of time comp combined with sleep
deprivation combined with postpartum
problems combined with hormonal changes
all of that together you may in some
individual cases get this kind of thing
and this is why I brought up the factual
stuff about her previous conduct and
history. Like I I really think about
whenever we think about stories like
this about trying to putelves myself in
the shoes of some of the people involved
where I can relate. If I put myself in
the shoes of her husband and I go my
wife who's up to this point been the
model mother and everything perfect. I
come home I find out she strangled our
children and tried to commit suicide. A
thing we didn't mention uh in our
factual introduction. I can totally
understand why he says she's not evil.
She She was just sick. Because if that
was to happen to me, I'd obviously be
horrified and devastated, but I'd be
like going, "This is completely out of
character." So, whoever did this is not
my wife as I understand her. Something
has happened in that situation. And I
know that people like very much to make
these comparisons with, you know, the
guy who stabbed Arena Zerutsko or the
this the the paranoid schizophrenic who
stabbed people. But I think we also have
to recognize that your prior conduct
really matters. Both of those, if I
remember correctly, had a long and uh
extensive deranged criminal history. So,
we're talking about people who have a
consistent pattern of behavior that was
not dealt with because of various
concerns, fears, the way the criminal
justice system works, etc. It's not the
case here. You're talking about somebody
who went from being effectively a model
citizen to suddenly strangling her three
children in some kind of fit. Uh, and I
think the these are very different
things. And so I I totally understand
why there's a big campaign about
sympathy for her, but more broadly
understanding mental illness in relation
to to to these things. And the other
thing as well, we've got to be honest,
there is a massive difference between
the pattern of male violence and female
violence. Um, and I think that's
relevant in the situation as well. I
think on that just quickly because
what's interesting is that a lot of the
nuance around essentially culpability
where serious mental illness is
concerned when people want to suspend
that discussion depends on the politics
and the optics of the situation. So go
back to the sort of Valdo Calane example
who wasn't who from what I understand it
kind of deteriorated over a period of
years wasn't unlike the kind of arena
situation wasn't a kind of down and out
criminal per se but was a student and
was had a series of episodes which were
violent and weren't dealt with. Um in
that situation there were a lot of
people on the the right who were kind of
reflexively saying I don't care about
these mental health claims. He should he
shouldn't be in a medical facility. he
should be in prison when it was quite
clear that he was in the midst of very
deep paranoid schizophrenia was
convinced that the state were spying on
him that all of these things which were
really kind of textbook and clearly
guided his behavior. Then you get the um
some of the commentary certainly on the
right around the Clansancy trial seems
to be because of the response to and the
commentary around the case has been just
sort of so easily folded into a sort of
narrative around kind of toxic
femininity and the idea why are all
these women seeing themselves in them
that therefore again she should not only
be locked up but potentially um that she
should be potentially you know actually
killed as a consequence of um what she
has um committed there. So again, I
think it's one of those things where
it's just become another feature of the
of the culture or not particularly
useful fashion. I suppose where I find
it a bit strange though is again that
level of identification with and that
level of sort of sympathy for because we
can recognize that someone does
something absolutely horrific when being
quite literally out of their mind. But
at the same time to see one's own
struggle in that person I think is a
little bit strange. And also we we kind
of see this conflation going back to a
point that Francis was making earlier of
the kind of forms of should we say me
like mental health issues if we're going
to use that phrase around postpartum,
whatever um thing, what used to be
called the baby blues, you know, the the
the um very very common experiences of
women after having children with this
most extreme example we could possibly
think about. And I think it does get to
grips with an issue that we've had for
so long in our public discussions around
this is that we talk so much about
mental health and the idea of it being
in its most minor forms often, you know,
barely diagnosible and definable issues
um is something which we talk about
endlessly. Meanwhile, very clear-cut
mental illness and the way in which it
completely can destroy a person's
psyche, leave them a danger to
themselves and others is something which
is, oddly speaking, a le a less sexy and
interesting issue, even though it's much
more consequential and serious in cases
like this. So, being able to disagregate
those two things, I think, is really
important if we're ever going to get a
cleareyed sense of not just cases like
this, but how we think about this issue
in general.
>> Well, and it's also as well, Tom, we
simply don't know how to deal with this
issue. We don't know how to deal with
serious mental illness. We don't know
how to deal with the these these people
when they're uh when they're a danger to
themselves or to others. And in
particular in the States, this is true.
I mean, go around any city in the United
States in the city center and you will
see people who are profoundly mentally
unwell, unable to take care of
themselves, posing a danger to
themselves and maybe to other people as
well.
>> What do you mean? terrifying
walking around a lot of these places.
It's terrifying.
>> I'm saying Yeah. No, I'm I'm saying but
they may be posing a danger to other
people or to themselves or
>> I I'm saying it's not there's no maybe
about it. They routinely attack other
people and and because they they are in
that state. And it's because, by the
way, I don't know if you know this, but
I suspect you do. It's because uh you
know uh there there was a point there
was a big uh anti-institutionalization
movement in America which basically said
that uh the way to help people who by
the way in those days often were held in
institutions where they were badly
treated and those institutions were you
know not up to the standards that we
would want them to be. Um the way to
deal with that is to let these people
out onto the streets because that's
freedom. Uh and that's, you know, that's
it's liberating them from the
constraints of institutions. That's why
you have the the zombie hordes that you
do see in in in the centers of major
American cities.
>> No, absolutely. So, and then but that
speaks to a to a wider problem which is
nobody as of yet has a solution to this
very very important issue that actually
affects a lot of people. And you and is
actually it's a kind of damning
indictment about our society as a whole
because if you're not going to look
after people and at the risk of sounding
what who are actually truly vulnerable
and can't support themselves and are a
danger to themselves or others then
we've gone we've gone wrong somewhere.
Well, I don't want to put a can of worms
on this, but it's it's a bit. So, if you
like take somewhere like California,
billions is being spent trying to deal
with this problem of what is mental
illness, but on the surface level
homelessness and drug addiction. Um the
the it's not a question of a desire to
try and do something about it is that
that they their ideology around the
problem is so twisted
>> that they that they actually are making
things worse because they're
incentivizing the bad behavior. This is
something that I know you've had Michael
Shelonburgger on your show. He's been on
my show a couple of times and he's
exposed this and and really shown this.
So I think that the society does
actually want to help this. But
progressive ideology in particular in
places like California is exacerbating
the problem. Well, this is why I brought
up the deinstitinstitutionalization
movement because actually I do think
there is an answer to this which is if
someone is a danger to themselves and or
other people, then they have to be in a
facility where yes, they are deprived of
their liberty for a period of time until
we can be certain that they're no longer
in danger to themselves or others. Uh
those are unpleasant trade-offs of this
terrible reality that mental illness is
a thing that that exists. But throwing
these people out into the street to to
smoke fentinil and be uh the the victims
of the most horrific life circumstances
is not the solution. Uh I feel that that
in the short history of off the fence
that has been the most on the fence
segment that we've had [laughter]
actually trying to be nuanced about it.
But look, I think it we we live in this
era of sloppialism where every issue is
presented as a sort of black and white,
good versus evil debate between, you
know, the men who are correct to dump
all their girlfriends and the women who
who have gone all of them have gone
mental over this. I really don't think
that if you're splitting up with your
girlfriend because she has a slightly
more sympathetic uh understanding of
someone who had a terrible mental
episode, you're probably an idiot.
Anyway, um there's me off. It's a new
Brexit, Constantine.
>> It's [laughter] a new Brexit. Exactly.
Uh, final story o of the week, uh, is,
of course, Andy Burnham is back.
Francis,
>> he's back. Back again. Uh, tell a
friend. So I actually think this is
possibly the most important story of the
previous week or rather this week that
wasn't really covered but actually
speaks to a very real problem that our
country has and is going to dominate
conversation either directly or
indirectly and that is Andy Bernham
refusing to rule out tax increases in
the new budget. So he refused to rule
out tax rises. He was also promised by
2030 to increase the defense spending to
3% of GDP. So he's already promised to
spend more money there. Cost of
government borrowing has risen to its
highest level in 18 years. We have a
100% debt to GDP ratio. Debt interests
cost us around 120 billion a year. Some
economists say a little bit lower, some
some say higher, but that's pretty much
the average figure. And our debt now is
double what it was after the financial
crisis in 2008.
And when Andy Burnham, and this is where
it gets really interesting, when he was
asked when he was blaming essentially
the reasons for our current financial
wos, do you know what he blamed it on?
It's Let's play leftwing bingo, gents.
Come on. What did he blame it on?
[laughter]
>> Thatcher, Brexit, um the far right. Who
else is got to be list Trump?
>> No, it's Brexit. It It's Brexit. It is
um It is uh Thatcher. There's one more.
>> It's not list trust, is it?
>> No. Come on. It's the word beginning
with a
>> the billionaire.
>> Austerity.
ity. There you go.
>> So,
>> well, Thatcher is a funny one, isn't it?
Because Thatcher was, of course, became
prime minister before any of us were
born and and sadly, we're no longer that
young. So, it's incredible. Uh, I was
going to mention, oh yes, the reason I
brought up Liz Trust, of course, is we
all remember how she crashed the British
economy famously, according to all the
media. Well, unbeknownst to the media
class who who promoted that story as
vigorously as they did, bond yields this
week are higher than they were at the
peak of the list trust crashing of the
economy. Um, now that's not to say the
list trust did everything perfectly.
Certainly not. But I think there's just
this general financial illiteracy in the
media class and uh increasingly in the
political class that comes with it as
well, which is why we're having this
conversation. process.
>> No, abs. Absolutely. And this is a
conversation that we're going to
continue to have because
the path and the trajectory that we are
on is quite simply unsustainable for
this country and we are going to have to
make some decisions and we're going to
have to make some very difficult
decisions and these are decisions which
are going to make the current political
party and the leader unpopular. Now,
where Andy Bernham is is I would argue
that he's at the peak of popularity
because he hasn't had to make any
decisions yet. But unfortunately for him
and he is going to have to get and I
quote off the fence at some point and
actually take some political decisions
particularly fiscal ones if we are going
to progress and turn the sinking ship
that is the UK economy around.
>> I think it's quite rare situation in
which the substance of the prime
minister we have and the scale of the
problems we face are so mismatched. The
same was true of Karma, but we're kind
of expected to be even pleasantly
surprised that Andy Bernham can like
string a sentence together. You got
bordering on bankruptcy, as you say,
Francis. The borders are still broken.
We've got this like glorified bus
conductor who has managed to find his
way into number 10. It's a really
dispiriting spectacle. And part of the
reason that obviously the markets are so
skittish is because Andy Bernham was Mr.
I don't want to be in hot to the bond
markets not too long ago. And this is
the problem. You might not want to be in
hot to the bond markets, but we are in
hot to the bond markets. You can lament
the fact that um we have allowed
ourselves to become so exposed that that
is the case and you could put in place
policies to bring down the debt over
time in a significant way to pursue the
kind of policies which would not only be
good in terms of easing market tensions
but would also be good for society
getting on top of the welfare bill
ending the the kind of social tragedy
that is so many people being put out to
pasture and all of the sort of
downstream fiscal effects of that. Um,
but you can't just wish it away. And it
seems that what we're the problem with
Andy Bernham, I think that we we're
gonna end up with is that partly because
he doesn't have his own mandate. And
therefore, even if he wanted to have
some sort of drastic break with starism
or Thatcherism or any kind of ism, he
kind of couldn't. Um but also because of
the just inability to get anything
vaguely sensible through the Labour
backbenches these days who have become
kind of captured by what is often
euphemistically called the soft left but
is basically the most vibes based
unprincipled we just we're labor and we
do nice things kind of section of the
party. um that is we're just going to
have loads of trundling along like it's
just going to be walking of a kind of
tight rope not wanting to do anything
that would seem unfair to this section
of society or unkind towards those who
supposedly need to be in receipt of the
enormous state large s which is now laid
on towards them. Um, so we're going to
it's just going to be more of the same,
I dare say. And I think whilst that
might change if an early election comes
our way or what have you, we're kind of
doomed to continuity starism where this
is concerned, which is not anything that
anyone should be excited about.
>> It's a really interesting point you make
particularly about the the fact that,
you know, Bernham famously said he
doesn't want to be in hawk to the bond
markets. We Britain is so like that
position is like a bit like a 35year-old
who still lives with his parents and
borrows money from them every month
going I don't want to be in hawk to my
parents. Well, stop living [laughter]
under their roofs anymore.
>> Yeah.
>> Didn't have to make it personal, mate.
But you know, [laughter]
>> you'll get out of there one day,
Francis. Don't worry.
>> Yeah. Look,
>> you know what I mean? It's like if you
keep borrowing money from people
[laughter]
>> Yeah. Yeah, if you keep borrowing money
from people, you will be in hawk to
them. And for the reasons that Francis
laid out beautifully, we are now
extremely in hawk to them. In fact, uh
you know, one of the things we talked
about the bond yields, Britain is paying
a premium. I don't know if you know
this, we were we're all similar age. I
think certainly in in in my 20s and
early 30s the the the the basket case
countries of the world of Europe were
Greece and Italy. We now have higher
bond yields than both Greece and Italy
in this country because our economic
policies our government's policies have
created a situation where we are less
trusted to repay our debts than Greece
and Italy. That is the reality. Um, and
you know the the the point about this is
the the the biggest problem with all of
this is none of it will be solved by the
policies that are being advocated for or
pursued because raising taxes is not
going to solve this problem. Uh because
you cannot tax even more to pay for all
this spending that we can't afford. The
we spend more on welfare now as we said
earlier in this conversation than we
raise in income tax. This is insane.
This is insane. And by the way, it's not
all scers. It's not all people who've
been, you know, uh, abusing the system.
A lot of it is people who simply don't
have jobs because of the economic
policies that our government's pursued.
And a lot of it, by the way, is because
we have an aging population of
pensioners who continue to vote for
policies that protect and support them
at the expense of their children and
grandchildren. Um, and uh, that is
another massive problem that no one
wants to talk about. And it's also so
many of the problems that are unique to
this country like just very quickly
sorry wisdom is that things like the
growth in sickness benefits and outwork
benefits amongst the young um which is
you know the idea that the young would
become a particular area of interest for
the welfare state just grates against
what the whole point of it was to look
after the old and the sick and so on you
know and the destitute rather than those
who actually should have a bit of get up
and go that's often blamed as a kind of
postcoid thing whether that relates to
mental health or longcoid or some kind
of bollocks like that you look at other
European countries you do not see that
pattern repeated. So there have been
particular decisions that we have made
in this country which have made the
issue so much worse and there's there's
a kind of refusal to grapple with that.
That's just a constant kind of gesture
to how terrible it is across the piece
and what have you and uh the fact that
these are factors almost entirely out of
the government's control. That's just
not good enough. There's things that you
can do, you can act and you can try and
deal with and clean up the mess of a lot
of what has happened in the quite recent
past that would start to amend this. you
know, you don't have to have a reckoning
with um 40 years of failed policy, as
Andy Bernon might see it, to get us back
on the right track, even in the near
term. I think,
>> just to add even more detail, 30-year
bond yields are now at the highest
they've been since 1998.
The
problem we've got is that there's
looming tax increases without serious
talks about decreases or or sorry
without decrease elsewhere or welfare
decreases and they just so I'm not to to
be contrarian here or uh I'm not
actually against some certain tax
increases if they're offset with
decreases elsewhere.
what Burnham is doing uh is so the the
the other big thing and this is a guy I
keep an eye on called Lord Jim Neil.
He's famous because he he's a Labour
grandy. He took coined the term bricks
and he was a JP Morgan and it was rumor
there was some rumors that Gary
Stevenson was going to be the uh
economics adviser for Bernham which was
all nonsense but it it was more true
that Jim O'Neal was and he and and Jim
turned it down because and he said he he
didn't want to give up his business uh
his businesses and dealings but he's
someone really worth keeping an eye on
because he would have given Burnham a
seriousness in government because he's
someone who does understand the bond
markets and does understand how to work
a budget in a way that would keep the
markets and the city uh uh settled. Um
he has said this week that
capital gains tax increases are looming.
Now I don't want capital gains tax
because it's going to be tax on me. But
I'm in theory not against capital gains
tax if there's massive reduction in
income tax and actually you you create
incentive for people to to work. What
we're seeing is just more tax
and no real decrease in in welfare. So
things can only get worse. But the most
offensive thing to me of all of this is
watching Andy Bernham's PNQs and his
various videos from cabinet meetings and
the amount of times he says uh or um he
puts the in Burnham and it [laughter]
fitting that that Burnham as a word
starts with an ends with an M because
those are the two sounds I basically
only hear from that Man, it is so
offensive to me that he talks like that.
It's so frustrating to hear. Can he not
does he not have convictions? Can he not
just speak shoot from the hip? What does
What do you think, man?
>> That thing drives me more insane than
the tax talk by orders of magnitude.
>> So, it
the big issues.
>> I was going to say, welcome to Off the
FX, where we give things their true
measure of priority.
The world in order. Exactly. Exactly.
Well, uh, gentlemen, that I think is us
for the week. Thank you, uh, for being
here. Thank you, uh, for watching and
listening. Make sure you subscribe to
Trigonometry, the Winston Marshall Show,
and of course, Spiked. And share this
with a friend. Share this with
everybody, and we will see you same time
next week.